Evernote, one of the biggest and most
ambitious products in tech history.
225 million users, hundreds of millions
in funding, and a goal to pass 1 billion
users and become a 100-year startup. But
now, no one uses it or even remembers
it.
What happened to Evernote?
Think about how you take notes. You open
your phone, write it down, or take a
picture. Before the smartphone, it was
pretty chaotic. Everything you wanted to
remember, shopping, errands, and
address, you wrote it down or just had
to remember. Some people would bring a
physical notebook to do so. And if you
had to keep receipts for reimbursement,
like gas, you literally had to hold on
to those receipts.
Then, you'd lose them or couldn't find
which notebook they were in.
That's the problem Stepan Pachikov
wanted to solve. Pachikov had spent
years building handwriting recognition
software, technology that ended up being
pretty much every tablet and stylus
device. If software could recognize
handwriting, why stop there? Why not
build something that could recognize
everything?
Then, in 2008, after 6 years of building
and prototyping, he had Evernote.
Evernote was designed as a kind of brain
backup. Once installed, you could store
anything, business cards, receipts,
handwritten notes, name tags, and the
software would make them searchable.
You could even take photos without text,
and Evernote would tag them by context
and location.
Your phone can do this today, but this
was 2008. Being able to search receipts,
handwritten notes, even photos, this was
unbelievable. This was a game-changer.
Pachikov understood another quiet fear
in business, forgetting names. If you
didn't grab someone's business card,
networking was extremely difficult.
So, just scribble down their name and
number and search for it with Evernote.
I really like the concept of endless
tape and for many years I was looking
for some suitable database to
conveniently record all sorts of memos,
jokes, notes, tasks, whatever.
This quest has become one of the
prerequisites for the birth of the
Evernote concept. Even though Evernote
was invite-only at the time, demand was
growing quickly. So, on June 24th, 2008,
Evernote officially launched as a public
cloud-based application and oh boy, was
it growing.
By the end of that year, it had over
500,000 users, 14 million notes, and
multiple platforms including a strong
mobile version.
But, there's another reason Evernote was
taking off. To find out, we need to
briefly step back to the most important
change in Evernote's history.
In May 2007, Pachikov stepped down and
handed control to Phil Libin, believing
he would be the better CEO.
Libin pushed for the freemium model. He
wanted everyone using Evernote and this
gave them the best chance of that. "We
don't care if you pay, we just want you
to stay around and keep using it and get
all your friends to use it. The longer
you use the product, the more likely you
are to fall in love with it and sooner
or later you'll be happy to pay for it."
And
he was right. Within a year of launch,
Evernote had been downloaded 1.7 million
times on desktop alone with over 1
million active users.
Evernote was exploding, but Libin had
much bigger plans for Evernote. In the
meantime, Evernote raised $9 million
from angel investors and began preparing
for its first major venture round,
something that was far from easy at the
time.
But, there was one other factor driving
this growth, timing.
Evernote launched alongside the rise of
the iPhone, the best device to showcase
Evernote's power. By 2010, Evernote was
available on Windows, Mac, iPhone, and
BlackBerry with over 3 million users.
And by the end of 2011, Evernote was
even profitable. Annual sales were 16
million. It was the 2011 company of the
year.
It then rose to 80 million users and
raised $250 million.
Evernote was now worth $1 billion.
Everything was going great, but here's
where things get a bit weird. Phil Libin
had a massive vision for this company.
So much ambition, in fact, that it would
eventually cause Evernote's downfall.
If you're any kind of busy professional
or freelancer, you know that to-do list
never gets shorter. There's always
another report, another presentation,
and the bigger stuff keeps getting
delayed because you're buried in
everything else.
What if you could delegate those
unfinished tasks and focus on what
really needs your attention?
This video is sponsored by GenSpark, an
all-in-one AI workspace.
They're Silicon Valley's first AI agent
unicorn, and they've reached a $250
million annual run rate in their first
year. Instead of chatting with AI and
still doing everything yourself, you
give GenSpark a task and it actually
finishes it. It orchestrates multiple AI
models, including Claude, Gemini,
ChatGPT, Nano Banana, and many more.
So, I wanted to see how far I could push
it. I opened their AI sheets and gave it
a giant spreadsheet of agency data.
Then, I gave it a real problem and data.
Jobs running over deadline, pushing back
upcoming projects, and the sales team
keeps adding more work.
I told it I also needed a slide deck for
Monday. It analyzed then restructured
the data, adding new pages of insights,
calculated how much this agency is
losing, and the high priority changes.
Then, in the same conversation, it built
a full slide deck for Monday's company
meeting.
Pretty awesome. Then, just for fun, I
set up a workflow that analyzes my
channel performance every week, which
runs automatically.
Genspark is offering a get-started
bonus. New users can try premium
features like web app building and deep
research with free credits available
upon sign up.
Try Genspark with the link in the
description below. Thank you to Genspark
for sponsoring this video.
Evernote wasn't the first startup Phil
Libin had run. It was his third, but
this time he was determined to make it
his last. Not just as a successful
company, but as a lifelong startup. Our
goal is to build a 100-year startup.
We're about 4 and 1/2 years into that. 4
and 1/2% done.
He also said the team had no exit
strategy, meaning no plan to a bigger
company as many startups do. They had
big plans for an IPO and a vision of a
billion users. Libin had a lot of vision
for the world of tech as well.
>> The line between consumer and business
is completely fading. In fact, I think
that 5 years from now, there will be no
such thing as a successful enterprise
uh software company that's not also a
successful consumer software company. Or
even product company, because I think
like modern knowledge workers are going
to demand the same quality experience
everywhere in their lives. And so, it's
the same people who use Evernote in
their personal lives and who use it at
work.
>> Keep these claims in mind because
they'll be important later. With Libin's
ambition, Evernote began to expand a
lot.
Being a 100-year startup meant
constantly launching or acquiring new
productivity software, and launch they
did.
First, Evernote Sketch, a visual note
app. Then, Penultimate, a popular
handwriting app.
Then came Evernote Trunk, and an
ecosystem connecting over 200
third-party apps. So,
what's the problem?
Well, Evernote was expanding out wide,
but not deep.
Soon, it felt like anything you can
imagine had an Evernote version, from
Evernote Food to Evernote Hello to
Evernote Work Chat to Evernote Business.
Evernote was no longer just a
note-taking app. Somehow, it was trying
to become a lifestyle brand.
Even though Evernote had over a million
paying customers at the time, the cracks
were forming. Every expansion and every
acquisition meant more hiring, more
scaling, more expenses, more need for
revenue.
A hungrier Evernote, which brings us to
a flaw in Libin's plan.
Many users just weren't upgrading to
premium because they didn't have to.
So, in 2016, the company restricted it
the free version while raising prices
for paid plans.
The economics of Evernote didn't make
sense until this point, as most users
had no real incentive to move to a
premium subscription. Users weren't too
happy, especially those who had years of
memories now heavily restricted. Though,
there were many more problems.
With Evernote growing wider, execution
quality was lagging.
Bugs piled up, updates stagnated, and
marketing seemed to outweigh product
development. Users flooded Evernote's
forms with complaints.
Editing notes on the web is painful. If
I paste text, the screen jumps back to
the top. If I paste a list, it gets
indented with a blank top line.
If I try to delete the blank line, it
deletes what's before it. If you have a
developer at Evernote try to write a
simple article in the editor, they will
find how subpar the editor is.
It's so obvious the editor is so behind
in functionality. They could fix it if
they wanted to. Heck, even the editor in
this form is way better than in the app.
But, it gets worse.
One change pushed users from annoyed to
angry.
To improve its machine learning,
Evernote changed its privacy policy. It
granted select employees access to
users' own notes, and to make it worse,
you could not opt out. Loved using
Evernote? Sorry, their new privacy
policy means I'll be moving my notes
somewhere else. They ain't for engineers
to pick through.
Evernote went into damage control. After
receiving a lot of customer feedback
expressing concerns about our upcoming
privacy changes over the past few days,
Evernote is reaffirming its commitment
to keep privacy at the center of what we
do.
But, the damage was done. The 100-year
startup was looking a bit shaky, and
unfortunately, it was about to get
worse.
While Evernote had been stumbling, their
competitors had been working hard to
make them obsolete.
Evernote might have faded away, but
we're still growing.
We're trying to reach 1 million
subscribers, so if you could help us
out, it would mean a lot.
You've probably been thinking something
throughout this video.
Evernote basically does what Google Keep
or Apple Photos does. And
you're right.
Search for a word like dog or grandma in
your photos, and it should be pretty
accurate. Even receipts or texts, most
apps can handle that.
It's not just photos either. Pretty much
everything Evernote does has a better
competitor.
Simplenote, Apple Notes, Notion,
Microsoft OneNote, Joplin, Obsidian, the
list goes on and on.
Also, most had little constraint on
users who don't pay a subscription.
Microsoft's OneNote went as far as
introducing a data migration tool for
Windows users wanting to make the
switch.
Were these apps better?
Maybe. They lacked some features
Evernote had, but they were better in
the ways that mattered.
Most of them were simpler, cheaper,
easier to use, and more reliable.
And this was a huge problem for
Evernote, which was still having all
kinds of issues. By the mid to late
2010s, Evernote was openly
restructuring, laying off staff, and
replacing leadership.
Libin, the architect of the 100-year
startup vision, stepped down as CEO in
2015 and left the company entirely in
2016.
Two years later, it was even more
dramatic. The CTO, CFO, CPO, and head of
HR all exited within 2 weeks.
And this was right as Evernote was
trying to secure more funding.
Then in 2018, they changed CEOs again.
Evernote was collapsing, and there were
multiple reasons.
The new CEO, Chris O'Neill, said, "We
committed too many resources too
quickly. We built up areas of our
business in ways that have proven to be
inefficient. Going forward, we are
streamlining certain functions like
sales, so we can continue to speed up
and scale others like product
development and engineering."
He was right, but it was too late.
Evernote laid off 15% of its staff,
which brings us back to Libin's grand
vision for tech.
He believed the line between business
and consumer products would disappear,
but he was only half right.
Evernote's business model was focused on
consumer-first growth, relying heavily
on popularity and a strong public image.
It worked, but big tech companies like
Google and Microsoft sold directly to
businesses and made much more money,
better margins, and a better conversion
rate.
In a 2019 survey asking, "How
disappointed would you be if you could
no longer use Evernote?", the product
scored just 23%, with only 64 out of 277
respondents saying they would be very
disappointed. Only 21% reported using it
every day, while over 75 respondents
used it just once per month. Evernote
was supposed to be a daily product. This
was bad. Yet, by this point, Evernote
had reached 225 million users. A lot,
but the highest it would ever go.
Evernote began to fade into irrelevance.
Users left, downloads declined, then it
was acquired.
The app is still around. Some people use
it, but it's now just a shell of its
former self.
Things haven't improved much, either.
Evernote wasn't killed by any one single
app. They had just lost focus. They
pivoted left and right, adding new
features and new toys that most people
didn't care about. They went wide and
shallow instead of narrow and deep.
While they were distracted, they
neglected their core product and
customers. So, those customers went
elsewhere.
Not only that, they bet on consumer
revenue and thought they could win both
the business and consumer markets, and
they didn't. The lines were blurred, but
not as much as Livin thought. Instead of
building a product that's secure,
reliable, and fast, Evernote has spread
itself too thin, trying to build out its
install base across as many platforms as
possible in an attempt to fend off its
inevitable competition. It doesn't
matter if your product is first or even
the best. Dominance is temporary. You
have to keep winning a customer over and
over with less friction than anyone
else.
Another company which exploded, then
seemingly disappeared, was wish.com.
Their ads were everywhere, and they even
got an offer from Bezos himself.
The story of Wish is even wilder. Click
here to learn the rest of the story, but
until then, I'm Harry, and I'll see you
guys on the next one.